the final example we're going to do is a
incredibly important example of a vector
field one
that comes from just a normal old scalar
function f
of x y and z a a function from r
three in this case just to r well for
such a scalar function
you could take what we called previously
in multi-variable calculus the gradient
the i-hat component is the partial
respect to x the y-hat is the partial
with respect to y
and the k-hat is the partial with
respect to z
that is if you give me a scalar function
f from either r2
or r3 to r then i can give you a vector
field a corresponding vector field given
by the
gradient of f the gradient of f is a
vector field
and it also has a very nice geometric
meaning
so for example suppose that my function
was the function f of x y
equal to x squared plus y squared then
we could compute out what its gradient
is not too bad well the partial respect
to x is just 2x and the partial respect
to y
is just 2y so the gradient is just that
now we've seen this vector field except
for the fact that there's a 2 in both
places which just stretches every vector
by a multiple of 2.
this is precisely the vector field we
saw earlier
and so now i can put everything together
in one picture so this is my
picture for this function what we see is
the graph of the function that's this
blue paraboloid
and then in the domain the domain is the
x
y plane we get a vector field in that
domain
and so i plotted the gradient vector
field in the domain
and then this function above the domain
and
as you might recall from multi-variable
calculus
the gradient vector points in the
direction of steepest
increase of your function so if you're
at some particular x and y-coordinate
and you're up there on the function
value at that x-y coordinate you want to
know
how do i climb this mountain represented
by this function as fast as possible
where is this function steepest what
direction should i go you should go in
the direction of the gradient
i hope you enjoyed this video and if you
did please give it a like for the
youtube algorithm because we're all
mathematicians here and we appreciate
algorithm just as much as youtube does
if you have a question leave it down in
the comments and
we'll do some more math as always in the
next video